Guide to the Arthur Gottschalk Academic and Professional papers, 1964-2019 MS 091
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Arthur Gottschalk Academic and Professional Papers
1964-2019
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gottschalk, Arthur
MS 091
14.5 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
This collection contains copies of autograph scores, lecture notes, articles, and programs from composer Arthur Gottschalk's academic and professional files. The materials in the collection date from 1964 through 2019.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Gottschalk attended the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor, receiving a Bachelor of Music degree in Music Composition, a Master of Arts degree in Music Composition and English Literature, and his Doctorate in Music Composition, studying with William Bolcom, Ross Lee Finney, and Leslie Bassett. He is currently a Professor at Rice University's Shepherd School of Music, where he served as Chair of the Department of Music Theory and Composition until 2009. He founded the university's electronic and computer music laboratories, and was the Director of the laboratories until 2002.
"Rapturous, argumentative, and prickly" (Gramophone Magazine), and "fascinatingly strange" (BBC Music Magazine), composer Arthur Gottschalk accepted an invitation as Visiting Artist at the American Academy in Rome in 2016, and The Association of Rice Alumni honored him with its Meritorious Service Award, the highest honor for a non-graduate of Rice University. Among many other awards, his Concerto for Violin and Symphonic Winds won First Prize in the XXV Concorso Internazionale di Composizione Originale (Italy), and in 2011 he was awarded the prestigious Bogliasco Fellowship for further work in Italy. Other awards include the Charles Ives Prize of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the 2014 Gold Medal for his Sonata for Cello: In Memoriam and the 2015 Gold Medal, Best of Show, and Recording of the Year from the Global Music Awards for his Requiem: For The Living. Residencies include the Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center, the Piccolo Spoleto Festival, and the Atlantic Center for the Arts.
(Biography taken from Gottschalk's Shepherd School of Music website)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains copies of autograph scores, lecture notes, articles, and programs from composer Arthur Gottschalk's academic and professional files. The materials in the collection date from 1964 through 2019.
Access Restrictions
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586. Box 12 is stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Conditions Governing Access
These materials are open for research except for one folder of professional papers. Access to this folder requires written permission from Professor Gottschalk. Contact Woodson staff for instructions at woodson@rice.edu or 713-348-2586.
Index Terms
Subjects
Composition (Music); Composers; Music
Document Types
programs (documents)
- Series I: Academic & Professional papers
  - Articles, Notices, & Reviews, 1973-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, Notices, & Reviews, 1995-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, Notices, & Reviews, 2003-2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles, Notices, & Reviews, 2011-2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles, Notices, & Reviews, 2014-2019 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards & Certificates, 1969-2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2005-2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2017-2019 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 1982-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2006-2010 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2011-2013 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2016-2017 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Festivals/Conferences, 2018-2019 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Professional papers (Restricted) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Conditions Governing Access
    These materials are restricted. Access to these records requires written permission from Professor Gottschalk. Contact Woodson staff for instructions at woodson@rice.edu or 713-348-2586.
  - Programs, 1964-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1982-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 2005-2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 2011-2013 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 2015-2016 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 2016-2017 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series II: Autograph and Printed Scores
  - Arrangements (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Belle Fernande (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Charlie's Ear (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chicken Soup (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Children of the Night, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Circus Encore (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cycloid, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - De Colores (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Deep in the Heart (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Fantasy Variations (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Illuminations (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Jeu du Chat (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Night Flight (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Paris (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Phases (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Quartet in One Movement (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Requiem for the Living (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Section (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Suite Concertante (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Superstructures (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Session (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - The Sophisticates, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Toussaint Overture (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Tricolor (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - What are You Doing? (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Zorba! (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Communiqué, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dark Songs, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Leyenda, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Roulades, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Beati Omnes, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Concerto for Wind & Percussion Orchestra (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Blue Fantasy (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Colors (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Close Encounters/Listening Song (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Fakebook (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Fanfare for a Great City, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ontogeny (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Overture: Measure for Measure, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Slide Show (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Stations (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Substructures, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Triad for Symphonic Wind Ensemble, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - American Nights, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Brodwick Songs, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The Blackberrry Hill Rag, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The Kaleidoscopic Pocket Hockets Boogaloo, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sonata for Bass Clarinet & Piano, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Suite Nothings, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Two American Hymns, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cycloid, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Fanfare, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Into the Maelstrom (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Motet, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Night Flight, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Night Play, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Phases (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Psalm 27, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Session, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Substructures I, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Variants II, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Untitled works/works in progress (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series III: Oversize materials
  - Oversize posters, 1978-2012 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Printed Scores
  - Amelia, 2012 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - America the Beautiful, 2013 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - American Nights (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Anthem: Come Light (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Sonata for Bass Clarinet and Piano, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Beat (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Blackberry Hill Rag, 2010 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Brodwick Songs, 2012 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Brunetti Variations (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Boogaloo (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Benny, Zoot, and Teddy (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Capriccio Genovese (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Sonatina Casada (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Cello: Fishing at Antibes (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Cello Sonata (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Celtic Drumline (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Ceremonial Fanfare (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Charades, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Come, Light (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - The Consecration of the Fatted Calf (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Contrary Variants (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Dark Songs (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Doo Wop Deconstruction (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Fakebook (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Fanfare for Michael (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Fanfaronade (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Fantasy Variations (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Five Songs of Love (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Fountains (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Heavy Metal (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Holiday Fanfare (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Sonata for Horn (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Jeu du Chat (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Flight of the Killer Bees (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Loss (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Overture: Measure for Measure (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Oh, More or Less (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Paradisum (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Psalm 27 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Grand Rag-Tango (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Royal Australian Regiment Brass (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Recuerdos de México (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Reformation Celebration (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - Requiem for the Living (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - Concerto for Brass Clarinet and Chamber Orchestra (Rollo Parisi) (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - 220 S. Michigan Ave. (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Sonata for Alto Sax (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Section (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - Shall we Gather (Box 12, Folder 49)
  - Slide Show (Box 12, Folder 50)
  - Sonatina Casada (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - At the Space Age Vinyl Music Box Lounge (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - Stations (Box 12, Folder 53)
  - Suite Nothings, 2012 (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Toussaint Overtour, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 55)
  - Sonata for Tenor Trombone (Box 12, Folder 56)
  - Sonata for Bass Tuba (Box 12, Folder 57)
  - Two American Hymns (Box 12, Folder 58)
  - Concerto for Violin and Symphonic Wind Ensemble (Box 12, Folder 59)
  - Western Sonata for Trumpet, 2013 (Box 12, Folder 60)
  - Whack! (Box 12, Folder 61)
  - Tebe Boga, 2018 (Box 12, Folder 62)